Leo Pfeffer Papers
Leo Pfeffer Papers
1942-1974
Pfeffer, Leo, 1910-1993.
22.5 linear ft.
The papers of the American lawyer, activist for separation of church and state, legal counsel for the American Jewish Congress, and director of its Commission on Law and Social Action consist of correspondence, legal briefs, dockets, court transcripts, essays, speeches, and printed material, including articles, clippings, pamphlets, periodical issues, and general files relating to civil rights, federal aid to education, prayer in public schools, and other church-state issues.
149517
Biographical History
Leo Pfeffer (1910-1993) was among the most prolific constitutional scholars of the late twentieth century. Pfeffer analyzed the Establishment Clause of the First Amendment from a "separationist" standpoint, arguing that this constitutional provision requires strict separation between church and state. From this perspective, government may offer no assistance to specific religions or religion in general. [From Encyclopedia of Religion in American Politics (1999)]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Leo Pfeffer Papers comprise 7 series: Conference transcripts, Published material, Legal material, Notes, Writings, General files, and Miscellaneous.
Conference transcripts include documents addressing subjects such as religious instruction and holidays in the public schools, church-state separation, and the Bill of Rights. The Published material is made up of pamphlets addressing civil rights and the separation of church and state. The Legal material series mainly comprises Litigation dockets, Court transcripts, and briefs. Notes include Index cards and a Notebook kept by Pfeffer. The Writings series comprises Essays, Magazine articles, Pamphlets, Journals, and Books. The General files series, making up more than half the collection, contains mostly Correspondence, plus some News clippings. Miscellaneous items include materials from a Bill of Rights conference and designs and proofs from Pfeffer's book, Church, State, and Freedom.
An expert on the United States Constitution, Pfeffer spent his career battling to preserve the fundamental American principle of Church-State separation. As a lawyer representing the American Jewish Congress, he authored Friend of the Court briefs for trials around the country. Most of the Legal material and General files therefore concern such issues as prayer in public schools, federal aid to parochial schools, and Sunday labor laws.
Subject and Genre Headings
Activism and social reform; Politics, government and public administration; Religion and philosophy; Pfeffer, Leo, 1910-1933.; American Jewish Congress. -- Commission on Law and Social Action.; Church and state -- United States.; Civil rights -- United States.; Federal aid to education.; Freedom of religion -- United States.; Hungarian Americans.; Jews, American.; Lawyers -- United States.; Prayer in the public schools.; Religion and state -- United States.; Religion in the public schools.; Constitutional law -- United States.; Briefs (legal documents); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Dockets.; Essays.; Galley proofs.; Legal documents.; Legal instruments.; Manuscripts for publication.; Transcripts.; Lawyers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Conference transcripts
  - Religious Instruction in the Public Schools, 1946; 1 vol. (Box 1)
  - Sectarianism in the Public Schools, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Religious Holiday Observance in the Public Schools, 1949; 1 vol. (Box 1)
  - Church-State Separation in the Public Schools, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Bill of Rights, 1966; 3 folders (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Pamphlets
    - General (Box 1)
    - American Jewish Congress, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
    - Civil Rights (Box 1)
    - Separation of Church and State (Box 1)
    - Religion in Public Schools, 1959-1965 (Box 1)
- Legal material
  - Commission on Law and Social Action, American Jewish Congress, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Opinion briefs, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Litigation dockets, 4 folders (Box 1, 2)
  - Court cases, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Friend of court briefs, 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Congressional testimony (Box 2)
  - Supreme court decisions, summary and analysis; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Court transcripts, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Court transcripts, 2 folders, 2 vols. (Box 4)
  - Court transcripts, 63 vols., 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Court transcripts (Box 6)
- Notes
  - Index cards-bibliography, unidentified (Box 6)
  - Notebook: Anti-Semitism in America, 1950 (Box 6)
- Writings
  - Essays and articles (Box 6)
  - Religion, Education, and the Constitution (Box 6)
  - Galley proofs (Box 7, 8, 9)
  - Typed manuscript - unidentified, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Church, State and Freedom -Index (Box 10)
  - Essays and articles, 7 folders (Box 10)
  - Judaism, Fall, 1974 (Box 10)
  - Magazine articles, 4 folders (Box 10)
  - New Testament Study (Box 10)
  - Pamphlets, 1972 (Box 10)
  - Books
    - Church, State, and Freedom, 2 vols. (Box 11)
    - Church and State in the United States, 1 vol. (Box 11)
    - Creeds in Competition, 2 vols. (Box 11)
    - The Liberties of an American, 2 vols. (Box 11)
    - This Honorable Court, 2 vols. (Box 11)
  - Pamphlets
    - "Assault upon Freedom of Association" (Box 11)
    - "The Supreme Court and the Bill of Rights" (Box 11)
  - Journals
    - Civil Rights in America (Box 11)
    - A Journal of Church and State (2 issues) (Box 11)
    - Current History (Box 11)
    - Michigan Law Review (Box 11)
    - United Synagogue Convention Proceedings, 1965 (Box 11)
- General files
  - 1958 (Box 12)
  - 1959, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - 1963 (Box 12)
  - 1964 (Box 12)
  - 1972 (Box 12)
  - Adoption, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - American Jewish Congress, 1970 (Box 12)
  - Anti-Defamation League, 1966 (Box 12)
  - Articles about Mr. Pfeffer (Box 12)
  - Becker Amendment: Bible Reading in School (Box 12)
  - Blue Laws, Sunday (Box 12)
  - Calendar reform, 1964 (Box 12)
  - Capital Punishment Case, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Chamberlain, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Chinese Language in Hawaiian Schools, 1949 (Box 12)
  - Church, State, and Freedom, 1953 (Box 12, 13)
  - Church-State Relations
    - 1948-1962, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - 1955 (Box 13)
    - 1965 (Box 13)
  - Congress Weekly (Box 13)
  - Correspondence
    - American Jewish Congress
      - 1954-1957 (Box 13)
      - 1955-1961 (Box 13)
    - Civil Rights, 1946-1950 (Box 13)
    - Conscientious Objectors, 1963 (Box 13)
    - Dover Zoning Law, 1949-1951 (Box 13)
    - Integration, 1957-1959 (Box 13)
    - Inter-Religious Adoption – Goldman Case, 1955 (Box 13)
    - Job Oath of an Atheist – Torcaso, 1959-1961 (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
    - Prayer in School – Famous Professors Voice Protest, 1962 (Box 13)
    - Religious Education in Public Schools, 1949 (Box 13)
    - Rosenbluth Book, 1968 (Box 13)
    - School Aid, 1966-1968 (Box 13)
    - Speaking Engagements
      - 1958 (Box 13)
      - 1961 (Box 13)
      - 1962 (Box 13)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 13)
      - 1969 (Box 13)
    - Television debate, 1961; See also General files: Television debate (box 19); 4 folders (Box 13, 14)
    - Zeller vs. Huff, 1948 (Box 14)
    - 1942 (Box 14)
    - 1945, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - 1945-1946 (Box 14)
    - 1945-1949 (Box 14)
    - 1945-1955 (Box 14)
    - 1946, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - 1946-1949, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - 1946-1953 (Box 14)
    - 1947 (Box 14)
    - 1948 (Box 14)
    - 1948-1970 (Box 14)
    - 1949 (Box 14)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 14)
    - 1949-1955 (Box 14)
    - 1950 (Box 14)
    - 1950 (Box 15)
    - 1950-1953 (Box 15)
    - 1950-1955 (Box 15)
    - 1951 (Box 15)
    - 1951-1959 (Box 15)
    - 1952, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - 1953 (Box 15)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 15)
    - 1954, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - 1954-1956 (Box 15)
    - 1954-1957 (Box 15)
    - 1955, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - 1955-1957 (Box 15)
    - 1956 (Box 15)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 15)
    - 1957, 3 folders (Box 15)
    - 1957-1958 (Box 15)
    - 1958 (Box 15)
    - 1958, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - 1958-1961 (Box 16)
    - 1959 (Box 16)
    - 1960 (Box 16)
    - 1960-1965 (Box 16)
    - 1961 (Box 16)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 16)
    - 1961-1967 (Box 16)
    - 1962, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - 1962-1965 (Box 16)
    - 1962-1968 (Box 16)
    - 1963 (Box 16)
    - 1964 (Box 16)
    - 1965, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - 1966, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - 1967 (Box 16)
    - 1967, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - 1967-1970 (Box 17)
    - 1968, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - 1969 (Box 17)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 17)
    - 1970 (Box 17)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 17)
    - 1974 (Box 17)
  - Creeds in Competition, 1958 (Box 17)
  - Dade County Schools, Florida (Box 17)
  - Di Censo (Box 17)
  - Florida Presbyterian College, 1960 (Box 17)
  - Hokkaido Law Review Reprint – Church and State, 1966 (Box 17)
  - Housing Discrimination, Jones Case – St. Louis, 1967 (Box 17)
  - Humane Slaughtering Bill
    - 1956, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - 1957 (Box 17)
    - 1958 (Box 17)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 17)
    - 1958-1967 (Box 17)
    - 1959 (Box 18)
    - 1959-1961 (Box 18)
    - 1961 (Box 18)
    - 1961-1965 (Box 18)
    - 1965-1967 (Box 18)
  - Japanese Language in Schools, 1949 (Box 18)
  - Lecture bookings, 1966-1967 (Box 18)
  - News clippings
    - 1950 (Box 18)
    - 1951 (Box 18)
    - 1951-1955 (Box 18)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 18)
    - 1962-1964 (Box 18)
    - 1975 (Box 18)
    - Bible-Reading in School – Doremus Case, 1952 (Box 18)
    - Distributing Bibles in School, 1953 (Box 18)
    - Funding Religious Schools, 1968 (Box 18)
    - Job Oath of Atheist – Torcaso Case, 1961 (Box 18)
    - Krieger Tribunal – Nazi Concentration Camp, 1950; See also General files: Krieger vs. Mittelman (box 21) and Miscellaneous: Krieger-Mittelman Tribunal (box 25) (Box 18)
    - New York State Textbooks, 1968 (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 18)
    - Opposing Tuition Grants, 1968 (Box 18)
    - Parochial School Aid, 1951 (Box 18)
    - Prayer in Public Schools, 1962 (Box 18)
    - Released Time, 1948 (Box 18)
    - Reviews
      - Church, State, and Freedom, 1953 (Box 18)
      - "Religion, Education, and the Constitution", 1948 (Box 18)
    - Sabbath vs. Unemployment Compensation
      - 1948 (Box 18)
      - 1951 (Box 18)
    - School Aid
      - 1950-1951 (Box 18)
      - 1961 (Box 18)
      - 1966-1968 (Box 18)
    - Work on Sabbath, 1949-1951 (Box 18)
  - Parochial School Busing, 1946 (Box 19)
  - Political Science Teaching Appointment, Long Island University, 1964 (Box 19)
  - Released time
    - 1945 (Box 19)
    - 1952 (Box 19)
  - "Religion in a Free Society", 1958 (Box 19)
  - Religion in Government (Box 19)
  - "Religion and Public Education", 1947 (Box 19)
  - Reviews of Mr. Pfeffer's Books (Box 19)
  - Senate Judiciary Subcommittee, Hennings, 1955 (Box 19)
  - Sioux City Cemetary Restrictions, 1954 (Box 19)
  - Speaking invitations
    - 1951-1969 (Box 19)
    - 1955-1969 (Box 19)
  - Speeches, 1958-1961 (Box 19)
  - Sunday Laws, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Television debate – Parochial Schools, 1961; See also General files: Correspondence: Television debate (boxes 13 and 14) (Box 19)
  - Unemployment benefits and Sabbath
    - 1948 (Box 19)
    - 1954 (Box 19)
  - Yarmulka – in School, Court (Box 19)
  - Zoning, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - 1960 (Box 20)
  - Becker Amendment: Prayer in School (Box 20)
  - Bible in Public School, New Jersey, 1952 (Box 20)
  - Bible Reading in School – Doremus Case, 1952 (Box 20)
  - Brighton, New York – Zoning Laws Prohibiting Churches, 1954 (Box 20)
  - Censorship of Film, "The Miracle", 1953-1957 (Box 20)
  - Correspondence
    - 1948-1950 (Box 20)
    - 1949 (Box 20)
    - 1950 (Box 20)
    - 1951 (Box 20)
    - 1952-1954 (Box 20)
    - 1957 (Box 20)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 20)
    - 1966 (Box 20)
  - Creeds in Competition Press Release (Box 20)
  - Darwin in Arkansas School, 1968 (Box 20)
  - Di Censo, 3 folders (Box 20)
  - Flast vs. Gardner (Box 20)
  - Flast vs. Gardner (Box 21)
  - Fountain Street Church, 1969 (Box 21)
  - Humane Slaughtering Bill, 3 folders (Box 21)
  - Immigration, 5 folders (Box 21)
  - Krieger vs. Mittelman, 1950; See also General files: Krieger Tribunal (box 18) and Miscellaneous: Krieger-Mittelman Tribunal (box 25) (Box 21)
  - Lemon vs. Sloan, 1971 (Box 21)
  - Lincoln Square Project, 1956 (Box 22)
  - Lynch Child's Religion Case (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous
    - General (Box 22)
    - 1947-1968 (Box 22)
    - 1953-1960 (Box 22)
  - Missouri Civil Rights, 1948 (Box 22)
  - Mitchel Field Give-Away, 1962 (Box 22)
  - News Clippings
    - Adoption and Religion, 1955 (Box 22)
    - Pfeffer (Box 22)
    - Prayer in Schools
      - 1962, 3 folders (Box 22)
      - Miami, 1962; 2 folders (Box 22)
    - School Aid, 1968 (Box 22)
    - Tilton, 1969 (Box 22)
  - Oregon Textbook Suit, 1957-1961 (Box 22)
  - Prayer in School (Box 22)
    - General (Box 23)
    - 1961, 3 folders (Box 23)
    - Schempp vs. Abington, Pa., 2 folders (Box 23)
  - Released Time (Box 24)
  - Religion in Schools, 1951 (Box 24)
  - Separation of Church and State (Box 24)
  - Sunday Labor Suit – Kuperschmid, 1962 (Box 24)
  - Sunday Work Laws, 1949 (Box 24)
  - Supreme Court – Aid to Public Schools (Box 24)
  - Ten Commandments (Box 24)
  - This Honorable Court Reviews (Box 24)
  - Tilton
    - 1969 (Box 24)
    - Correspondence (Box 24)
    - Documents, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Unbound pages (Box 24)
  - Unemployment benefits and Sabbath, 1952 (Box 24)
  - Voting in Churches, 1969 (Box 24)
  - Zoning – St. Louis vs. Temple Israel (Box 24)
- Miscellaneous
  - Bill of Rights Conference, Long Island University, 1966
    - Guest register, 1 vol. (Box 25)
    - Pamphlets (Box 25)
  - Krieger-Mittelman Tribunal – Nazi Concentration Camp, 1950 (Box 25)
  - Life Magazine Article, "You Are the Man Who Killed My Brother.", See also General files: Krieger Tribunal (box 18) and Krieger vs. Mittelman (box 21) (Box 25)
  - Church, State, and Freedom
    - Cover design (Box 25)
    - Computer-printed proofs (Box 25)